<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cesars due and the subjects duty, or, A present for Cesar in a sermon preach't in the Minster at Yorke at the assizes there holden Aug. 3, 1663 by way of recantation of some passages in a former sermon preached in the same place and pulpit at the last assizes immediately before it / both of them by Thomas Bradley.</title>
            <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 63 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B08550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4129</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R212809</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">69648533</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 69648533</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184859</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B08550)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184859)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2877:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cesars due and the subjects duty, or, A present for Cesar in a sermon preach't in the Minster at Yorke at the assizes there holden Aug. 3, 1663 by way of recantation of some passages in a former sermon preached in the same place and pulpit at the last assizes immediately before it / both of them by Thomas Bradley.</title>
                  <author>Bradley, Thomas, 1597-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Alice Broade and are to be sold by Richard Lambert at the Minister-Gates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Yorke :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Taxation --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tithes --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:184859:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>COncionem hanc, cui Titulus,</hi> Ceſars Due, and the Subjects Duty, <hi>molliendis hominum Animis, Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> deprecandae habitam Eboraci à Rdo Viro</hi> Tho: Bradley <hi>S. T. P: legi, perlegi; &amp; quia à ſummâ ad imam uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ejus chordam nihil uſpiam reperire eſt niſi quod eò plurimùm faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at, Typis proinde publicis mandandam cenſui</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Edm: Diggle,</hi> S. T. P. Reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſimo in Chriſto Patri ac Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mino Domino Archiepiſc'. <hi>Eborac'.</hi> à ſacris domeſt'.</signed>
               <dateline>Epiſcopo-Thorpae <date>
                     <hi>Aug:</hi> 11. 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184859:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CESARS Due, <hi>AND The Subjects Duty:</hi> OR, A PRESENT for CESAR.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>IN</hi> A Sermon preach't in the Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at <hi>Yorke,</hi> at the Aſſizes there hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den <hi>Aug.</hi> 3. 1663. by way of <hi>Recan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation</hi> of ſome Paſſages in a former Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Preached in the ſame place and Pulpit at the laſt Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes imediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it.</p>
            <p>Both of them</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> Thomas Bradley, <hi>D. D. Praebendary of the Cathedrall &amp; Metropoliticall Church there, and Chaplain to his late Majeſty of bleſſed Memory;</hi> Oxon' Exon'</p>
            <p>
               <hi>YORKE,</hi> Printed by <hi>Alice Broade,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Lambert</hi> at the Minſter-Gates, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:184859:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:184859:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Mathew 22.21.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Give unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are a cautious An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to a captious Queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to our bleſſed Saviour by the Herodians, not ſo much for ſatisfaction, as for Cavill, that they might entrap him, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare him, and that in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer they might catch ſomething from him, whereof they might accuſe him unto <hi>Ceſar.</hi> Four ſuch Queſtions were there propoſed to him in this Chapter by four ſeverall Sects or ſorts of people; all which took their turnes to oppoſe him, and took <hi>placet</hi> one of another to diſpute with him; The Sad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces, the Phariſes, the Scribes, and the Herodians. The firſt three of theſe he had eaſily ſhaken off, and gave them ſuch full ſatisfying or convincing Anſwers that they had no heart to ask him any more Queſtions, <hi>ver:</hi> 46. But now in the 4th place comes in the Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:184859:3"/>and he charges moſt dangerouſly and deſperately of all the reſt, both in reſpect of the matter of his Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and of the manner of propoſing it. Firſt for the matter of it, all the other Queſtions were concerning matters of Religion; this matters of policy, and of State, and that in a point of high concernment, about <hi>Ceſar's</hi> Revenue, the Tribute money: As to the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of propoſing it, all the reſt in plain down-right termes propoſe their Queſtions, but the Herodians goe more ſubtlely to work; for firſt, to avoid all jealoſie, and to prevent all ſuſpition of their evill intentions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, they court him with a fair co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plement <hi>Maſter,</hi> ver: 16. Secondly, they give a large teſtimony of him for his wiſedome &amp; courage, ſincerity &amp; impartiality in teaching the wayes of God truly, and not regarding the perſon of Man, and to all this they themſelves ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe <hi>Scimus,</hi> We know it: And thus having by their hypocriticall flattery and diſſembling Inſinuations laid their traine, they give fire to it, and propoſe their <hi>Quaere, Licetne? is it lawfull to give tribute to Ceſar or not?</hi> But what an inſidious Queſtion was this? and how dangerous for him to anſwer to, what a horned <hi>Dilemma</hi> that puſh't both wayes, Anſwer which way he could; for had he reſolv'd in the affirmative, <hi>Licet,</hi> it is lawfull, and you muſt pay it, then had he ſet the Phariſes againſt him, which could not endure to hear of any ſuch <hi>Taxes</hi> or <hi>payments:</hi> or had he reſolv'd it in the negative <hi>non licet,</hi> it is not lawfull, and you need not pay it, then had he incurr'd the juſt diſpleaſure of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and the Herodians, as an enemy to his Revenue;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184859:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo that take it which way he would, he had a Wolfe by the ears, and guide as ſteadily as he could (on the one ſide or on the other) he was in danger to be bitten.</p>
            <p>But in vain is the Nett ſpread before the eye of that which hath wing; full well did our Saviour ſee the fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, and the policie of this ſubtle Queſtion, and diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Aſſes ears under the Lyons skinne, and as wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and warily did he ſhape his Anſwer, to avoid their ſnare, not by anſwering their Queſtion, but by asking them another, unto which they could not anſwer him, but they muſt anſwer themſelves too to the Queſtion which they put to him, and condemne themſelves for making a Queſtion of it; <hi>Whoſe Image and ſuperſcription is this? ver:</hi> 20. as if he ſhould ſay, you will all confeſs that to your <hi>Ceſar,</hi> your Soveraigne, there is a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute due from his Subjects, and you muſt acknowledge that he whoſe Image you do own upon your coyne, whoſe ſtamp upon it, and ſuperſcription or circumſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion about it, makes it currant amongſt you, is your <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> your Soveraigne, why then do you ask me this Queſtion, to which (in this ſolution you have given to me) you have anſwered your ſelves? read your duty and <hi>Ceſars</hi> due, not out of my anſwer to you but out of yours to me, and out of the Coyne which you carry about you, and out of the ſuperſcription upon it, or circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription about it, that will tell you, that it is not only lawfull to pay it, but it is unlawfull not to pay it, and therefore <hi>Reddite Caeſars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Give unto Ceſar the things that are Ceſars</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:184859:4"/>
            <p> In which words here are three things offerd to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration.
<list>
                  <item>1. The Perſon to whom this Tribute is due, and that is <hi>Ceſar; Give unto Ceſar.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The things that are to be given unto him, with his right unto them, they are his own, <hi>The things that are</hi> Ceſars.</item>
                  <item>3. The manner after which they are to be given, and that is by way of rendition or returne, <hi>redite,</hi> render; thus <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars: And every one of theſe three parts car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries its reaſon in it, enforcing the duty, and ſo binds it upon us as with a threefold cord, not eaſily broken.</item>
               </list> Upon a review, every one of theſe branches divides it ſelfe into two, or hath two particulars included in it:
<list>
                  <item>In the firſt, the perſon of <hi>Ceſar</hi> is here offered to us; firſt to conſider of Government in general, with the benefits the Subjects receive under it: and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly more particularly of the Ceſarian or Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chicall Government in the Text the moſt perfect and abſolute of all other.</item>
                  <item>In the ſecond, the things that are <hi>Ceſars;</hi> here are two things to be conſidered; firſt what things they are, ſecondly the right that he hath unto them, becauſe the Text ſayes they are his own; <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars.</item>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:184859:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>In the third we are to conſider upon what account the Subject brings in <hi>Ceſars</hi> due, and that's by way of returne, in the word <hi>Redite:</hi> And ſecondly after what manner they ought to be brought in, and that's freely in the word <hi>give, Give</hi> or <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I begin with the firſt of them drawn from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the perſon to whom it is to be paid, and in him of Government at large, and the benefits that Subjects receive under it: For it is clear our Saviour mentions this as an Argument why they ſhould pay Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> becauſe he was their <hi>Ceſar,</hi> their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, and under his Government they received many benefits; even the benefits of Government. What <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Oratour ſpeaks to <hi>Felix</hi> the governour of <hi>Ceſarea, Acts</hi> 24.2. That may all Subjects in generall ſpeak to and of their Soveraignes reſpectively, and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame grounds and reaſons: <hi>Foraſmuch as by thee we enjoy much quietneſſe, and many good things are done to our Nation by thy Providence, we acknowledge and accept it all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and with all thankfulneſſe,</hi> (moſt noble <hi>Ceſar.</hi>) It is by their care and providence under God, and by their faithfull and prudent Government of us, and executing judgement and juſtice in the Land, that we enjoy our peace, our plenty, our liberty, our property, our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, our all that we have; Take away Government from among us, and what will become of us, and of all theſe? which of us can ſay that any thing that he hath is his own, or ſecure himſelfe of his life for one hour?
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184859:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Oh bleſs God for Government, certainly the greateſt bleſſing that ever God ſent down from heaven to earth in temporall things, is the bleſſing of Government, it is the very ſtay of the world, the band that holds all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, which once being looſed, it is impoſſible but we ſhould fall all into heaps of confuſion, and be reduc't again into the firſt Chaos; and therefore among all the creatures in the world the wiſedome of Almighty God the high diſpoſer of all things, hath ſet and eſtabliſhed a Government: If you look into heaven, there is Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and order; we read of Angells, and Arch-Angells, and a glorious Hierachy in the Church Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant: if you look into Hell (the very emblem of confuſion) there is a Government; we read of a Prince of Devills: if we look into all the Creatures between them both, we ſhall find a kind of order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amongſt them; the fowles of the ayre have their Eagle, the beaſts of the earth their Lyon; the Fiſhes of the ſea their Whale; even amongſt thoſe feeble Creatures the <hi>Sectilia,</hi> the Bees acknowledge a Maſter, the Graſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers have no King, yet goe they forth all by Bands, which ſhewes they have their Leaders; All Creatures in heaven, in earth, and under the Earth cry up Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and with one voice acknowledge it the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their peace ond joy. Therefore <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars, becauſe he is your <hi>Ceſar,</hi> your Soveraigne; and for the good you receive under him, the benefits of Government.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:184859:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> But ſecondly, as Government in generall is neceſſary among all, ſo among all ſorts and kinds of Government this in the Text, the Ceſarian, or Monarchichall Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment is the moſt perfect, the moſt abſolute, and excellent above the reſt. I will not here ſpend time to read amongſt you a Lecture of Politiques, to ſhew the ſever all kinds and formes of Government wich are found amongſt men, nor put them into the Ballance to weigh them, and to compare them one with another: there are but three principall ſorts which ſtand in competiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for preeminence, <hi>Democracy, Ariſtocracy,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy;</hi> among all which, Monarchy holds up its head above the reſt, as the Cedar among the ſhrubbs, or as <hi>Saul</hi> among the reſt of the common people, higher by the head and ſhoulders, and hath clearly the preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence in five reſpects.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the Nobleneſſe of it, it is the moſt noble forme of Government, and that which moſt neerly reſembleth that whereby Almighty God governeth the world, and thats purely Monarchicall. What were all the Governments of the world to the four great Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chies, the Aſſyrian, the Perſian, the Grecian, and the Roman, under which the world was governed for the greateſt part of the time ſince it was created; and whoſe ſame hath drown'd all other Governments in compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of them?</p>
            <p n="2">2. For the Antiquity of it, it is the moſt ancient of all other: It is a miſtake in policy to imagine that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchicall Government ſprang out of Politicall, as that out Oeconomicall, and ſo was meerly founded upon the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184859:6"/>conſent and agreement of men only; whereas it owns God only for the Founder of it, and is as ancient as the world, or man upon earth: The firſt man that was in the world was a Monarch, and that not only over his own Family (which he was by a paternall Right) but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the families of all the Generations which were in his time, which was little leſſe then a thouſand years. In <hi>Abraham</hi>'s time we read of <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> a King of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem; Moſes</hi> was a King in <hi>Jeſurun;</hi> and <hi>Job</hi> (in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babillity ancienter then <hi>Moſes</hi>) was a King in the Eaſt, as the Ancients tell us; ſo that neither was <hi>Nimrod</hi> the firſt Monarch, (as ſome would have it) nor <hi>Saul</hi> the firſt King; (as others) there were Monarchs ancienter then them both; and before Democracy or Ariſtocracy were caſt into formes of Government.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Monarchy is the moſt perfect forme of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in reſpect of the unity that is in it; it is the great happineſſe and fafety too of a People when they all as one man are united together in one body: this was the happineſſe of <hi>Jeruſalem, Pſalme</hi> 132 2, 3. <hi>Jeruſalem is a Citie that is at unity within it ſelfe.</hi> and <hi>Balaam</hi> ſpeaking of the many thouſands of <hi>Iſraell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Numb.</hi> 23. ſpeaks of them all as one man, <hi>God brought him out of Aegypt, he hath as it were the ſtrength of an Unicorn; he ſhall couch down as a Lion, and as a great Lion, who ſhall rouze him up.</hi> and in this language all along, he ſpeaks of them in the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular number, <hi>he, him,</hi> and <hi>his,</hi> all ſingulars; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares the whole body of them to ſome one Noble crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, a Lion, a Unicorne; all ſpeaking their unity, which was their happineſſe, their honour, and their ſafety too.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184859:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>But there is no forme of Government of that force to keep multitudes together in unity, as the Ceſarian or Monarchicall government is, wherein ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of people, of ſo many ſeverall Nations, ſeverall Languages, ſeverall Religions, ſeverall Cuſtomes, Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, manners, intereſts, or howſoever different one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> another: yet as the members of the naturall body (as different as they) united together under one head do concurre to the making up of one beautifull body natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall; ſo all theſe united together under one Head and Monarch, <hi>conveniunt in eodem tertio,</hi> and concurre to the making up of one body politique.</p>
            <p n="4">4. For ſtrength Monarchy hath the preeminence, <hi>vis unita fortior;</hi> it cannot be but where power and authority are united in one, it muſt needs be of greater force and ſtrength, then where it is divided and diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted amongſt many; and the ſtream running down in one channell muſt needs be more forcible, deep, and ſtrong, more impaſſable, and carry a deeper Veſſell, then when it is divided into many ſmaller Rivulets: the Perſians at the ſiege of <hi>Babilon</hi> found it ſo; and the ſage old Father in his death-bed, perſwading his ſonns to unity by the Emblem or Hieroglyphick of a faggot bound up and impregnable, and the ſame looſed, and the ſticks taken out ſingle, and ſo eaſily broken one by one, made them ſenſible of the ſtrength and ſecurity that was in unity, and the weakneſſe that was in diviſion, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to danger of ruine and of being broken in pieces; even ſuch is Monarchy in compariſon of other formes of Government, as a mighty ſtream running down in one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184859:7"/>channell, and they divided into many ſmaller currents: as a faggot ſtrongly bound up not to be broken, and they as a faggot looſed and divided, and ſo more eaſily to be dealt withall.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Monarchichall Government is the moſt excellent and perfect forme of Government of all oshers, becauſe it is moſt free from thoſe incenvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which they are all ſubject to, and with which they are uſually diſtempered and diſturbed. For <hi>Ariſtocracy</hi> the next unto it, how long will it continue free from the miſchiefs of ambition, envy, and emulation? how apt are great ſpirits (with <hi>Adonijah</hi>) to exalt themſelves, and grow impatient of rivality? <hi>through diviſions in</hi> Reuben <hi>ariſe great thoughts of heart: Nec ferre poteſt Caeſarvè priorem, Pompeiuſvè parem: Ceſar</hi> will endure no ſuperiour, <hi>Pompey</hi> no equall: and then the next is to make parties, to ſtrengthen themſelves, to accuſe and impeach one another, to weaken their adverſaries, that under theſe pretences they may carry on their own deſignes, and engage a whole Nation in their perſonall Quarrells, and embroile them in warr and blood to ſerve their ambitions. For <hi>Democracy,</hi> the ignobleſt of all the reſt, that placeth Soveraignty in the people; what a monſtrous <hi>Hydra</hi> is it, <hi>multorum capitum bellua?</hi> how unconſtant in theirs reſolutions? how tumultuous in their elections? how tormented with diviſions, and diſtracted with factions? what a low conſtitution at the beſt? allwayes fain to truckle under ſome neighbour Prince or other for protection, which at ſome time or other takes occaſion and advantage from their diviſions
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184859:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to fall upon them, and to make a prey of them; the uſual concluſion of moſt of them: beſides, how continually ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to change? the moſt dangerous miſchief in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the world. Denocracy is very apt to dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate into Anarchy, Ariſtocracy into Oligarchy, Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy into Democracy again; and thus they are in a continuall rotation, whirling and wheeling about out of one forme into another, none of which changes are ever made without the expence of much blood &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to the danger of ruine of their whole State: and therefore the wiſe man adviſes not to meddle with them that are given to change, <hi>Pro:</hi> 24.21. but marke it, in the ſame place he bids us fear the King, and from that Government never to deſire to change: neither is it ſo ſubject to change as theſe other are, being the <hi>apex</hi> and the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the higheſt kind of Government, from which neither Prince nor People have any reaſon to change for any other; not the Prince, for higher he cannot go, and he hath no reaſon to deſire to go lee; not the people of what degree or quality ſoever, becauſe they cannot mend themſelves, being where the meaneſt may have protection and the greateſt account it their honour to be near unto him who is the fountain of honour, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver think much to ſubmit to Soveraignity in a King, which to their Peers in Ariſtocracy they would not do, much leſſe to their Inferiors in Democracy.</p>
            <p>But how happy are we of this Nation in this reſpect, (if we could ſee our own happineſſe) which have the Quinteſſence and whatſoever is excellent in all theſe u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited together in one the moſt happy Government that
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184859:8"/>live under, and thats <hi>Monarchy limited by Law;</hi> the beſt of Governments under the beſt of Kings, <hi>CHARLES</hi> the ſecond. And this is a ſtrong argument to perſwade with us to <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars; And the firſt propoſed, we now paſſe to the ſecond, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in we are to conſider.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. What thoſe things are which we are to give unto <hi>Ceſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. What is his right unto them, becauſe the Text ſayes they are his, <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars</item>
            </list>
            <p>And I will acquaint you with the latter of theſe firſt, with <hi>Ceſars</hi> right to the things that are demanded of us, that he may demand them the more confidently, and we may bring them in the more willingly and freely. And a right you ſee he hath, the Scripture plainly ſpeaks it, when it calls the Tribute and other dues, the things that are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> and of this it is neceſſary we ſhould be fully perſwaded: It is a great miſtake amongſt men, yet generall amongſt the vulgar, to thike that whatſoever they part with to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> comes meerly out of their own ſtore of free gift, a meer Donative, a Gratuity, a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolence, that they might chuſe whether they will pay or no, and ſo he meerly an Eleemoſynary in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving of it; and therefore men uſually pay their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the Prince, as they do their Tithes to the Prieſt, with an ill will, as imagining they pay them both up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame ſcore of free Benevolence; but in both e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually miſtaken: for firſt, as for Tithes, they are none of theirs, they are the Lords, as a Rent reſerv'd out of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184859:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Lands, and he hath diſpoſed them as he hath thought fit, that is to the Church, and to his Miniſters: <hi>Tithes are mine</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and I have given them to the ſons of</hi> Levi: You may ſell your Lands, but you cannot ſell your Tithes; you may let your Land, but you may not let your Tithes; they are none of yours to let, they are the Prieſts: when therefore you pay your Tithes to the Prieſt, you pay no more then is his due, you give to the Prieſt the things that are the Prieſts. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner it is with your Tribute to the Prince when you pay Tribute to the Prince, you pay him no more then is his Due; you only <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars: it is not a matter arbitrary, whether you will pay it or no, but a matter neceſſary, you muſt pay it: it is not a courteſy, but a duty, not a gratuity, but a debt; St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly calls it ſo, <hi>Rom:</hi> 13.7.8. To detain it therefore is a ſin, not only againſt the Law of juſtice &amp; gratitude, but againſt a Principle of common honneſty. which commands us to give every man his own; and if every man then <hi>Ceſar</hi> amongſt the reſt; and therefore <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars:</p>
            <p>And there are three wayes by which <hi>Ceſar</hi> comes to have a right unto thoſe things which he requires of us, and ſo they become the things of <hi>Ceſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Thoſe things are <hi>Ceſars</hi> which belong to him in the right of his Crown, and which are inſeperably annext unto it.</item>
               <item>2. Thoſe things are <hi>Ceſars</hi> which the Law of God giveth unto <hi>Ceſar.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:184859:9"/>
               <item>3. Thoſe things are <hi>Ceſars</hi> which the Law of the Land giveth unto <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and which by Act of Parliament are ſettled upon him; and all theſe are ſtrong rights, and do give unto him an unqueſtionable Title to all thoſe things that are by all or any of theſe wayes made his.</item>
            </list>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe wayes, it werehigh preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in me to undertake to give in an account which are his in the right of his Crown; ſuch things there are, and they are great and many, which are flowers of the Crown, which no Subject may preſume to touch much leſſe to crop off, under pain of being guilty of an high Crime on taking away from <hi>Ceſar things that ere</hi> Ceſars.</p>
            <p>But ſecondly, thoſe things are <hi>Ceſars,</hi> which by the Law of God are given unto him, and they are great &amp; many, the Queſtion here moved is only concerning Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, <hi>Shall we pay tribute to</hi> Ceſar <hi>or not?</hi> but the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is larger then the Queſtion, and injoyns and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes not only Tribute, but all other dues whatſoever, <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars. And there are ſix things which by the Law of God are clearly given to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> firſt, <hi>Fear,</hi> 2. <hi>Honour,</hi> 3. <hi>Obedience,</hi> active and paſſive, 4. <hi>Defence,</hi> 5. <hi>Prayer,</hi> and 6. <hi>Tribute.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Fear, <hi>Proverbs</hi> 24.21. <hi>My Son fear thou the Lord and the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Honour, 1 <hi>Pet:</hi> 2.13. <hi>Fear God honour the King.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. Obedience, <hi>Eccleſ:</hi> 8: 2. <hi>I councell thee to obey the Kings command, and that becauſe of the Oath of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:184859:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <item>4. Defence, <hi>Pſal:</hi> 105.15. <hi>Touch not mine anointed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. Prayer, 1 <hi>Tim:</hi> 2.1. <hi>I exhort therefore, firſt of all, that ſupplications, prayers, interceſſions, and giving of thanks, be made for all men, eſpecially for Kings.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. Tribute, as in the Text and Context.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are all due unto <hi>Ceſar,</hi> and that <hi>jure divin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> by divine right, and thats the higheſt and the beſt right; and therefore if we fail in the payment of any of them, we are guilty of witholding from <hi>Ceſar</hi> his Right, we do not pay unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſars.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the queſtion here moved is particularly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning tribute the laſt of theſe ſix, and thats the very Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of the diſpute in the Text. 'tis fit I ſhould more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſpeak to it; for be you well aſſured, that not for their ſakes alone was this Queſtion here ask't, nor for their ſatisfaction alone, was the reſolution given to it, but for ours alſo, and for all Subjects in all places, and in all ages to the end of the world, (according to the ſeverall Lawes, Cuſtomes &amp; Uſages under which they reſpectively live) who would be as ready to queſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the due of it as they here were. I ſhall therefore endeavour to ſhew, firſt, from authority of Scripture. 2ly. from the example and practice of former times. 3ly. by ſtrong and unanſwerable reaſons, not only the juſtice &amp; lawfullneſſe, but the equity &amp; reaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of paying Tribute unto <hi>Ceſar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And firſt for Scriptures, they are clear and plentifull <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Render to every man his due, tribute to whom tribute belongeth:</hi> and in the 6 verſe, <hi>For this cauſe pay we
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184859:10"/>tribute.</hi> So there is a tribute to be paid, and there is a cauſe for it, which the Apoſtle there ſhewes at large. And of the four Evangeliſts, three of them have given this very charge, and in the ſame words, (an itteration not uſual in the Scripture unleſſe it be in ſome ſerious matter) which they would have well taught and learn't, <hi>Matt:</hi> 22.21. <hi>Marke</hi> 12.17. <hi>Luke</hi> 20 25. <hi>Rom:</hi> 13.6, 7, 8. <hi>Solvite,</hi> ſayes one Text: <hi>Redite,</hi> ſayes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother: <hi>Give,</hi> ſayes a third. <hi>As a Debt,</hi> ſayes one: <hi>As a due,</hi> ſayes another: <hi>As his own,</hi> ſayes a third. Thus you have it from Scriptures clear, with line upon line, precept upon precept, commanded and enjoyned, and by the Authority thereof a Revenue ſetled upon <hi>Cefar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly for Examples, ſee <hi>Solomon</hi> the wiſeſt of Kings, extraordinarily aſſiſted by almighty God for the Government of his people; he had his publique Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, and great Tributes paid in unto him for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port of his Government and for this purpoſe he had his Officers to gather them in in all his Provinces, and over all the reſt one great Officer of State to take their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dits and Accounts, his great Treaſurer as you may call him, that was <hi>Adoniram,</hi> he was over the Ttibute. 1 <hi>King</hi> 4.6. And after him <hi>Rehoboam</hi> his ſonne, who was King in his ſtead, had the like Officer in the ſame truſt, and that was <hi>Adoram,</hi> 1 <hi>King</hi> 12.18. he was over the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute. <hi>Amaziah</hi> levyed a Taxe, (2 <hi>Chron:</hi> 25.9.) of 100 Talents: <hi>Menahem</hi> another (2 <hi>Kings</hi> 15.19.20.) of 1000 Talents of ſilver, a great Taxe of 50 ſhekeles a man. In <hi>Auguſtus</hi> time there was a new taxe impoſed upon
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184859:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>the People, and it was a great one; there came out a Decree that all the world ſhould be taxed, that is, all that were under the Roman Empire, and theſe were extraordinary taxes (beſides the ſtanding Revenue) im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by a new Decree upon occaſion, and yet they were paid; where (in the laſt of them) the paines was more then the pay, for every one was to repair to his own Citie and Tribe that he belonged to to be taxed: <hi>Luke</hi> 2. In our Saviours time we read of certain Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers appointed on purpoſe to gather up this Tribute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>money among the Jews, they were called Publicanes, allwayes rank't with ſinners, and on the right hand: but what do we ſpeak of theſe? our Lord himſelfe did not only by his command enjoyn it, but by his example con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme and ſecond it; himſelfe paid tribute unto <hi>Ceſar, Mat.</hi> 17.27. what need we any further witneſſe?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As Scripture doth command it, and example confirme it, ſo reaſon doth perſwade it, and ſtrongly evince and demonſtrate the equity and neceſſity of it; and I ſhall give you theſe five reaſons of it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is drawn from the conſideration of his publique Office, his publique capacitie; you muſt not look upon <hi>Ceſar</hi> as a meer man, but as a Magiſtrate, as a man cloathed with majeſty, a King, a Soveraign, the head of the Tribes, a Collective perſon, in whom the many thouſands of Iſraell are united and repreſented; as the Sunne in the firmament, which hath influence upon all, and all an intereſt in him; as the ſoul in the body which by the ſpirits, the curſitors of it, conveyes life,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184859:11"/>and ſenſe, and motion to all and every even the leaſt Members of it; ſuch is <hi>Ceſar</hi> in his Dominions, as the Sunne in the firmament, and as the ſoul in and to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall body, ſo is he to the body politique. It is but reaſon that publique perſons in publique capacities ſhould be publiquely ſupported.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As <hi>Ceſar</hi> is a publique perſon, ſo 'tis for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique that he layes out himſelfe and that which he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives, for the publique behoof, for the publique ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for the publique good; as to himſelfe, what hath <hi>Ceſar</hi> of all that is brought in more then will ſerve one man? he eats no more, he drinks no more, he wears no more; whatſoever is uſed about him more then will ſerve him as a man, is to be charg'd upon his Office, not upon his perſon, it is to be imputed to him as in his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique capacity, not as a Man, but as a Magiſtrate, a Prince, a Soveraign, to fit and enable him for the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on of the publique affairs, and for the managing of the Government, in which we are all concern'd; and ſo in effect it is laid out for our own uſe, not unto his, who hath only the trouble of diſpoſing it for ours. All Rivers run into the Sea, yet the Sea is never the fuller, for what it receives in one place, it ſends forth in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the good of the whole Land; for part of it is exhal'd out of the ſea by the warmth of the ſunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beames, and ſo conglomerated into clouds, which are carryed about by the wind like bottles in the ayre (as <hi>Job</hi> calls them) and ſo power'd down in ſhowers to wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the dry and thirſty earth, and part of it is ſent and convayed out of the Sea through the Cavernes of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184859:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>earth (as it were by pipes and conduits, and being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecated in the paſſage of it from the ſaltneſſe that was in it) iſſues and breaks out into ſprings and fountains, and is convayed in rivers and ſtreams through the valleys of the Land for the comfort and refreſhing both of man and beaſt, even ſo and no otherwiſe is it with the <hi>Ceſar,</hi> the Soveraign in his Dominions, if he receives with on hand, he deſtributes with the other; he receives to have, but not to hold it returnes again in the bleſſings and benefits of Government, and therefore the detain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it is a wrong not ſo much to him, as to the publi<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> and to our ſelves involv'd in it. I have read ſome where of a mutiny that was raiſd by all the members of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>againſt the belly, <hi>The members complained and murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red againſt the belly that it devour'd all and wrought none, the reſt of the members did their parts to work and bring in ſuſtenance, and when they had done ſo, the belly devour'd it, and ſtill was calling for more;</hi> this they apprehended as a grievance, and for redreſſe in it (upon conſultation had about it) they reſolve and agree thenceforth towith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from the belly the uſuall Alimony and nouriſhment which formcriy they did afford it; but what was the iſſue of it? in with-holding their contribution of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed ſupply which formerly they did afford it, they did but puniſh themſelves; for ſoon after the face grew pale, the cheeks lean, the ſides thinne, the hands weak, the knees ſeeble, and the whole body waſted and in a conſumption: I need not apply it; ſay it is but a ſable, every Fable hath its Morall, and ſo hath this. There is mention made in <hi>Zach:</hi> 4. of a myſticall viſion:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184859:12"/>
               <hi>Zacharie</hi> ſees there a golden Candleſtick with a golden bowle on the top of it, ſeven Lamps burning in it, every Lampe had a golden Pipe belonging to it, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed oyle to it: and on either ſide of it was an Olive-Tree to furniſh the Pipes with a continuall ſupply of oyle, which they conveyed to the Lamps to keep them burning: there are many Interpretations of this viſion, but ſure this is plain enough for one, to ſhew that if you would have any light or benefit by the Lampes you muſt keep them burning; if you would continue burning, you muſt ſupply them with oyle: if you do either take away the Pipes or cut down the Trees which ſhould ſupply them with oyle, the Lamps will burn but awhile I leave to your ſelves the application of it. Certainly, if the ſuprea Magiſtrate as a great burning &amp; ſhining Light conſume himſelfe to give light to others, others have no reaſon to thinke much to ſupply him with oyle to keep him burning: and this is another reaſon why we ſhould willingly &amp; freely <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs that are</hi> Ceſars</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third reaſon is taken from the conſideration of the great charge that it requir'd for the managing of the Government of a Kingdome, and carrying it on with that honour and State that is but fitting and neceſſary: Government is a chargeable employment, there muſt be Navies abroad at Sea to ſecure the Coaſts, and to keep us ſafe at home; there muſt be Armies abroad and at home too, to ſecure us from inſurrections, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions and commotions; there muſt be Ambaſſadours ſent abroad into forraign Kingdomes and States both ordinary and extraordinary, and there muſt be Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184859:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>entertain'd from ſorraign parts to hold corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondence with the Nations, and to gain intelligence; there muſt be Courts of Juſtice and honourable Perſons ſitting in them to miniſter judgement and juſtice unto the people; there muſt be great Officers of State to be employed in the Publique affairs; there muſt be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable proviſions for the Houſhold, with a Port and Retinue becoming Majeſty; Debts of the Kingdome muſt be paid, publique engagements taken off, Soldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers muſt be paid off their Arrears; Men and Armes, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition and moneys allwayes in a readineſſe, and a thouſand things more which I cannot mention: all theſe require full Treaſuries; and whence ſhall all theſe ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies ariſe? or whence ſhould they ariſe? but out of the publique Tribute; <hi>Quis militat propriis ſtipendiis;</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it unreaſonable that any Soldier ſhould go a warfare in the ſervice of his King and Country at his own charge; much more unreaſonable &amp; impoſſible is it that any Prince ſhould mannage the Publique Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at his own charge: therefore <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth reaſon perſwading to this duty of paying Tribute to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> is taken from the conſideration of the great pains and care that is required in Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and which <hi>Ceſar</hi> takes in the execution of his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, &amp; the diſcharge of that high Truſt which God hath committed unto him. We little know, and leſs conſider what carefull thoughts their heads are taken up with night &amp; day, that all may be well under their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and that their ſubjects may be preſerved in peace and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184859:13"/>ſafety: <hi>Splendorem videmus, curam &amp; laborem non vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> we ſee the outward ſplendour &amp; glory of Courts, and that dazles our eyes, but the inward cares, troubles and dangers that attend them in the execution of their great Office and high Truſt, we ſee not: they often wake, when their ſubjects ſleep; their thoughts are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten troubled, when their ſubjects are quiet; they often in danger, when their ſubjects are ſecure, every one un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his own vine, and his own fig-tree, eating the fruit of his own labours, when their carefull thoughts will neither ſuffer them to eat, nor drink, nor ſleep in quiet that their Subjects may do ſo. Very ſenſible of theſe things was the Philoſopher, when he ſaid, <hi>That if men did but know the cares, the trouble, and the dangers that lye within the circle of a Crown, they would not take it up to wear it:</hi> and gravely <hi>Eraſmus, Miſeros eſſe Principes ſi mala ſua intelligant, miſeriores ſi non intelligant:</hi> that among all conditions of men, Princes were miſerable if they knew the evills that did attend them, and more miſerable if they did not know them. Very ſignificantly doth the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> call Government a burthen, a burthen upon the ſhoulders, no light burthen, ſuch as may be born with the hand, nor carried at arms-end, but ſuch a burden as he muſt put under his ſhoulder to bear it: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. where ſpeaking of Chriſt in his Office of ruling the People, he ſaith, <hi>The Government ſhall be upon his ſhoulders:</hi> ſuch is the condition of <hi>Ceſar,</hi> the Soveraigne in his Kingdome and Dominions; he hath his load, the Government is upon his ſhoulders, we have no reaſon by our diviſions and diſtractions to adde more weight
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184859:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>unto it, but rather by our contributions every one to ſet our hand to it to make it lighter. It is a remarkable expreſſion of the Prophet, which we read in the 78 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> where giving teſtimony of King <hi>David</hi>'s go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verning of Gods People, he ſaith thus, <hi>He fed them with a faithfull and true heart, and guided them prudently with all his power.</hi> where we ſee how many abilities are here met together to make a good Governour, here is <hi>faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe,</hi> and <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>tenderneſſe,</hi> and <hi>prudence,</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> and all theſe ſtrain'd up to the heighth to make him a good Ruler and Governour of Gods people; even ſo is it with all faithfull and religious Princes; they are fain to put forth all their power, prudence, wiſdome, knowledge, skill, and experience, and the utmoſt of their abilities, and all little enough in the governing of their people: we may take a conjecture of this in the Government of ſome leſſer Societies which we are better acquainted with, ſuppoſe it be but of a Colledge, a Corporation, or a Family; how hard a matter do we find it to governe them in peace, and to keep them in order? how much adoe have we to keep them from fac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and from diviſions, and to hold them together in unity? and yet if the Supream Magiſtrate do not ſo by all our Families, and all the Societies conſiſting of them, and by all his people in all his Dominions to the ſatisfaction and contentation of all Parties howſoever diſtracted and divided among themſelves, preſently we are ready to fall foul upon the Government, and to thinke hardly of him that hath the managing of it. The Greeks have a very ſignificant Proverbe amongſt them,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184859:14"/>and it ſpeakes ſomething to our purpoſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: There is one great ſervant in a great fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, and thats the Maſter; <hi>ſi licet exemplis in parvo grandibus uti:</hi> if I may make ſuch uneven Compariſon, 'tis true of great Princes in their Courts and Kingdomes aſwell as in a Maſter in a private Family, they are cal'd the great ſervants of State, and truly ſo they are (par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the expreſſion) and the greateſt care and burden, the weight of all lyes upon them. Let this be a fourth reaſon why we ſhould <hi>render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars; the ſenſe of the great burden that lyes upon him, the difficulty of Government, the danger he is expoſ'd to in the managing of it, the great pains and care that he takes to governe us with juſtice and to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve us in peace: therefore <hi>render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, give unto <hi>Ceſar</hi> the things that are <hi>Ceſar's</hi> for the good we recive under and by his Government, the very word in the Text imports as much, and implies that conſideration as the reaſon of the duty; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſayes the Greek; <hi>redite,</hi> ſayes the Latine, not <hi>give,</hi> but <hi>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> in both: but <hi>rendring</hi> preſuppoſeth a receiving firſt, what we render we do but reſtore what was before de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to us; we do but returne with one hand, what we receiv'd with the other; therefore give to <hi>Ceſar,</hi> becauſe you receive from <hi>Ceſar</hi> more then you give, and better then you give: and what is it that we receive from <hi>Ceſar?</hi> it hath been already ſhew'd in part, in the beginning of this diſcourſe; what do the ſublunary bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies receive from the Sunne? what do the members of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184859:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>the naturall body receive from the ſoul that animates them? the ſame do the Subjects receive from their <hi>Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> who is as the Sunne in the firmament of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes? and as she ſoul of the body politique of his Dominions. <hi>Daniell</hi> in his viſion, <hi>Dan:</hi> 4. ſets forth the benefits of Government under the emblem of a goodly Tree ſpreading forth his boughs and branches every way farre and near, even to the uttermoſt parts of the earth; the fowles of the ayre ſat in the boughs and branches of it, and the beaſts of the field, great and ſmall lay under the ſhadow of it; he adds further that the Tree was full of fruit, and all Creatures fed upon it, and had ſuſtenance from it: even ſo it is with a great Monarch in his Dominions, he is a univerſall good amongſt his ſubjects, and the influences of his Government flow forth to the utermoſt of his Dominions unto all ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Clergy and Laytie, great and ſmall, as well as the ſmaller Birds that ſit and ſing upon the lower or outward branches where they can get footing, as to the greater fowles that ſit upon the higher boughs &amp; top-branches of it, as well to the ſmaller Cattell that quarter on the outſides, as to thoſe more noble creatures, the Lyons, and Unicornes &amp;c. which quarter nearer to the body of the Tree; they all receive from him both food and ſhadow, ſhelter and protection, countenance and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and all, it is from the Tree, from the Monarch, inaſmuch as it is by his means, by his care and pains in the wiſe managing of the Government and in executing judgment and juſtice amongſt his Subjects that they do enjoy them, and are protected in them, as <hi>Tertullus</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184859:15"/>
               <hi>Acts</hi> 24.2. The Royall Prophet <hi>David</hi> was ſo ſenſible of this, that he ſeems in a manner to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute all that the Subject enjoyes to the King, as the royall fountain of Government and ſecurity, by which he ſtreams it out and conveys it to them: In the 2 <hi>Sam:</hi> 1.24. where exhorting the daughters of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to mourn for <hi>Saul</hi> their King now dead, he makes this his argument, becauſe living he did ſo much for them, and they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch benefits from him, even to the very garments which they wore; <hi>Ye daughters of</hi> Iſrael <hi>mourne for</hi> Saul, <hi>who cloathed you in ſcarlet, with other delights; who put on ornaments of gold upon your apparell:</hi> how did <hi>Saul</hi> cloath them which he never ſaw, nor probably they him, but a few of them? but only thus, that under his prudent Government and protection of them, they with their Parents and Huſbands thriv'd, and proſper'd, and grew rich, and were protected in the peaceable poſſeſſion and enjoyment of what they had, which otherwiſe they could not have been ſecur'd in: and upon this account <hi>David</hi> imputes it unto <hi>Saul,</hi> that they enjoy'd all theſe precious things from him, as if he had freely given them unto them, as it were out of his own Ward-Robe and Jewell houſe: <hi>Ye daughters of</hi> Iſraell <hi>mourn for</hi> Saul, <hi>who cloathed you in ſcar let, with other delights; and put on Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments of gold upon your Apparell.</hi> The caſe is the ſame, and the reaſon the ſame to all other Subjects under the government of their Soveraigns and <hi>Ceſars</hi> reſpectively; and therefore in the ſame language will I apply it to all ſorts of people among us, under a better Government then that was, and under a better King then <hi>Saul</hi> was.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:184859:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> Ye Daughters of <hi>England</hi> mourne for him that is gone, who cloathed you in ſcarlet, with other delights, and put on ornaments of gold upon your Apparell; but rejoyce in his living Image left behind, under whoſe happy Government and Protection you enjoy the like benefits, priviledges, and favours.</p>
            <p>Ye Ladies, which like the Lillies of the field neither ſow nor ſpin, yet <hi>Solomon</hi> in all his Royalty not cloath'd like one of you; remmember who it is that cloaths you in ſcarlet, with other delights; that puts on ornaments of gold upon your apparell, with gemms, and jewells, pearls, and precious ſtones, with which you are ſo illuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trious; be thankfull to him, glory in him, and rejoyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
            <p>You noble Lords and great Ones, whom he hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken near unto himſelfe, and made Princes of the firſt Liſt, in advancing you to Honours and Offices above others; remember who it is that cloath'd you with ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, with Robes and Ermins; who it is that put the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net upon your Heads, that put upon you the Collar and the Garter of Honour, and other Enſignes of greatneſs and of glory; be thankfull to him, glory in him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce before him who is the fountain of honour, and by whom to be honoured is your higheſt glory.</p>
            <p>You Right reverend &amp; holy Biſhops of the Church, the Chariots of <hi>Iſraell</hi> and the horſe-men thereof, whoſe very Robes ſpeak your Gravity, Innocence, and Purity; remember who it is that ſet the Mitre upon your Heads, that granted out your <hi>CONGE DELIERS,</hi> that cloathed you with Aaronicall Garments, garments
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184859:16"/>for beauty and for glory: be thankfull to him, glory in him, and rejoyce before him.</p>
            <p>You Reverend and learned Judges of the Land, whoſe honour and Office is to adminiſter judgement and juſtice unto the People; remember who it is that cloathed you in ſcarlet, from whom you receive your honourable Commmiſſions of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Terminer,</hi> and from whom you have your Authority delegated; be thankfull to him, glory in him, and rejoyce before him.</p>
            <p>You Reverend &amp; learned Academicks, Doctors, and Dignitaries, who have attained the higheſt degrees of Schools in either of the Univerſities, many of the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; remember who it is that hath cloathed you in ſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, and who is otherwiſe your high Patron, and munifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Benefactour; be thankfull to him, glory in him, and rejoyce before him.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Et ſpes, &amp; ratio ſtudiorum in Caeſare tantum.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>You rich Merchants, grave Citizens, honeſt and inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Countrey-men, all of all ſorts, remember from whom, and by whoſe means (under God) you do enjoy your peace, your plenty, your ſecurity, your protection, by whoſe care it is that the Ships ſail in ſafety, that the ſhops are open with ſecurity, that the Plough goes in peace, that you reap your harveſt quietly, and eat the fruits of your own labours; and thinke not much to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne an acknowledgment for theſe benefits; do not grudge and grumble to pay Tribute to whom tribute is is due, upon ſuch valuable conſiderations; and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully <hi>render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars: which brings in the third part of the Text ſhewing the manner
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184859:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>after which they ſhould be done, in the verb, <hi>Give,</hi> or <hi>Render.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That is, do it <hi>freely,</hi> do it <hi>fully,</hi> do it <hi>timely;</hi> As God, ſo the King loveth a chearful giver: diſputes &amp; delayes in theſe caſes are interpreted denials, &amp; <hi>viſcoſa beneficia,</hi> as the Philoſopher calls them, benefits or gifts which hang like Birdlime upon the fingers of thoſe that give them, as if they were loath to part with them, <hi>ingrata ſunt,</hi> they loſe their acceptance, and forfeit their reward; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore give, and give freely; render and render readily, not as upon conſtraint, but as of a willing mind; and ſurely if this muſt be done to a <hi>Tiberius,</hi> to a <hi>Nero,</hi> how much more and more chearfully to a <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> to a <hi>Theodoſius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here to ſtirre up all good Subjects to the ready performance of this duty, I intreat you to conſider with me theſe four things.</p>
            <p>Firſt, In what ſtate our <hi>Ceſar</hi> found this Kingdome, whenby Gods goodneſſe he returned to it; the Exche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer empty, the Crowne jewells &amp; goods ſold, yea the Crowne it ſelfe, with the Scepter, and Globe, and all the rich and precious things which his Royall Father and his Anceſtors had ſtor'd up and preſerved, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable value made away; The ward-Robes plundred and rifled, the Plate and houſhold-Stuffe in all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Pallaces taken away, yea the Pallaces themſelves pulled down and ruin'd, and the very materialls of them ſold; the Kingdome deeply in debt, in vaſt and incredible ſumms; a numerous Army of Horſe and foot deeply in Arrears to be paid off; a great Navy at Sea
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:184859:17"/>farre more chargeable then it to be diſcharged: to ſay nothing of his Majeſties own Debts, for we cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that he could live by the ayre ſo long in forraigne parts; ſo that his condition at his returne was much like unto our Saviours when he was upon the earth, that <hi>had ſcarce a place to lay his head, nor bread to put into it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, conſider what great things he had to do, and in part yet hath; to ſet in order a tumultuous Kingdom, and a ruinous Church, both of them ſo miſerably out of frame, that it is the work of an age to ſet them to rights again; to keep in pay great numbers of Horſe and foot for Guards and Gariſons, the reſtleſneſſe of diſconten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted people neceſſitating it; to pay off the Navy and the Armies, and the debts of the Kingdome; to build and to repair, and furniſh anew his Majeſties Royall Houſes and Pallaces demoliſhed, neither Crown, nor Scepter, nor Globe, nor Robes, nor Ward-robes, nor Plate, nor Houſhold-ſtuffe, nor any thing to ſpeak on left, except he would buy it anew with his penny, nor ſo much as bare walls to bring them to untill he build them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider his frugality ſince his returne, ſo far from waſt and profuſedneſſe in expences, that the very neceſſaries are very ſlender; for his houſhold pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, if you ſhould compare them with <hi>Solomons,</hi> you would wonder at the vaſt difference between them, in the 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 4. We have the conſtitution of <hi>Solomon's</hi> houſe a Liſt of his Officers, and of the Dyet and daily proviſion of his houſe, and this was his proviſion for one day, thirty meaſures of fine floure, and ſixty meaſures of meal, ten fat Oxen out of the ſtall, and twenty out
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184859:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>of the Paſtures, a hundred ſheep, beſides Harts, and Roe-buckes, and fallow-Deer, and fatted fowle; if you compare theſe with the houſhold of our preſent <hi>Ceſar,</hi> you will wonder at the difference, and yet his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes and Dominions are far greater and of larger ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent; but it ſeems his contribution and his Tributes are not ſo great. And take a conjecture of his frugality but in one inſtance more: Here have three of the blood-Royall (very near unto his Majeſty) dyed ſince his Majeſties coming in; the Funeral expences of all theſe three came not to the third part (I thinke I may ſay the thirteenth) of the expences of the funerall of the late Uſurper.</p>
            <p>Many other things might I alledge to bring on this duty with chearfullneſs &amp; readineſs, his unparalel'd ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, his invincible patience under them; his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in his religion againſt tryalls and temptations, not without much grace and ſtrength to be reſiſted; his ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious mercy ſhewed to his implacable and deſperate enemies; his indulgence to tender Conſciences; his ſtudious endeavours to compoſe all differences, to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie all parties, if it were poſſible; never did any Prince ſtudy his Subjects as he hath done.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, to crown all the reſt, he brought with him an Olive-branch, the emblem of peace; hath put an end to our civill-warrs; hath broken our ſwords into mattocks, and our ſpears into pruning-hookes; hath reſtor'd our Religion, reviv'd the Lawes, ſettled the Courts of Juſtice; hath under God, and God by him, made good to us and to our Nation that gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe made to the people of God upon their returne:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:184859:18"/>
               <hi>Iſa:</hi> 2. <hi>He hath turn'd his hand upon us, and purely purg'd away all our droſſe, and taken away all our tinne, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor'd our Judges as at the firſt, and our Councellours as at the beginning.</hi> Great are the things which God hath al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready done for us by him, and great things we hope he hath yet by him to do for us; <hi>haec ſi non moveant ſingula juncta movent:</hi> All theſe things ſurely may be of great force with all good Subjects freely to <hi>give unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars, and <hi>tribute to whom tribute be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth;</hi> tribute of Subſidies, tribute of Cuſtomes, Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage and Poundage, tribute of Firſt-fruits and Tenths, tribute of Taxe or Contribution, tribute of Confiſcati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons (from which the Treaſury hath its name <hi>fiſcus; Nehem:</hi> 10.8.) tribute of fines, tribute of Hearth-money, tribute of Exciſe.</p>
            <p>And becauſe this laſt is the tribute which is ſo much talk't off, and ſo much trouble hath been about it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of all other it is ſo much grumbled at, and comes in ſo hardly, and I my ſelfe have been complaind off for Preaching againſt it in this place and Pulpit at the laſt Aſſizes; it is very fit that in it I ſhould more clearly and fully declare my ſelfe, and in diſcharge of that duty, I do here openly, clearly and confidently declare and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, <hi>that the Exciſe as it is here eſtabliſhed in</hi> England, <hi>is</hi> (in the conſtitution of it) <hi>a Legall and juſt Revenue, and one of the Tributes here in the Text due unto</hi> Ceſar: and therefore if any man ask me as the Herodians did our Saviour in this Context, <hi>Licetne?</hi> is it lawfull to pay it or not? I anſwer as our Saviour did them; <hi>Licet,</hi> it is lawfull to pay it; it is utterly unlawfull not to pay it:
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:184859:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>fore <hi>Render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars. And that you may do it chearfully and readily, without murmu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring or diſputing, I will give you in ſome reaſons ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not only the juſtice and lawfulneſs, but the equity and reaſonableneſſe of it; and they are theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is eſtabliſhed by Law, and that ſilences all diſputes, it is ſetled by Act of Parliament as a part of the Revenue; and therefore a right not to be queſtioned.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to his Majeſtie he is no gainer by it, he hath parted with a very honourable Revenue in lieu of it, to wit, <hi>the Court of Wards,</hi> one of the faireſt flowers in the Crown, ſo fair, that the great Counſellour, Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burliegh,</hi> once Maſter of that Court, did in's death-bed adviſe Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> never to part with it out of her hands, for that it was an unknown Revenue, and one of her Majeſties beſt Farmes; but howſoever that being taken away, and only this left in the room of it, if we ſhould with-hold this too, what ſhall we leave him?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The third reaſon is taken from the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the ſubject out of which the Exciſe oth ariſe, the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modity on which it is impoſed, and thats ſtrong-drinke, an element upon which there is more thrown away in vain expence, then upon any one thing, nay, may I not ſay upon all other Commodities, in the Land; upon which, eſpecially in great Townes, and by many other perſons in many other places too, there is near as much thrown away in waſt as would reaſonably ſerve for all other neceſſaries: and in the exceſſive and intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate uſe or rather abuſe of which, there is more ſinne
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184859:19"/>committed and occaſioned in the Land, then about any other thing whatſoever: if then the wiſdome of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to take men off from this exceſſive and intempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate abuſe of it and themſelves, have laid ſuch a legall charge upon it, who can judge but that it was an Act of <hi>Wiſedome</hi> and <hi>Prudence,</hi> of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> in them for the reſtraining of abuſes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The laſt reaſon is taken from the freedom that men have to take up the profeſſion which makes them lyable to pay Exciſe, or not to take it up, to uſe it, or not to uſe it; there's no man compel'd to it, and if he like it not upon thoſe termes upon which he is to be Licenſed and admitted, he may let it alone, and there's no hurt done, if he like it not with the incumbrances, he may paſs by and leave it, and the Exciſe ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver trouble him: <hi>Volenti non fit injuria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon all theſe reaſons and conſiderations I conclude, <hi>That the Exciſe</hi> (in the conſtitution of it) <hi>is a juſt and a legall Revenue, that the impoſition of it upon thoſe commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties upon which it is laid, is no wrong to any man: that not only by law, but in reaſon and equity, it may juſtly be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and ought to be paid;</hi> and therefore I exhort and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh all perſons concern'd in it, not to diſpute it, not to quarrell it, but willingly and readily as in all other Tributes, ſo particularly in this of the Exciſe to <hi>Render unto</hi> Ceſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Ceſars.</p>
            <p>And ſo I have done with my Text, and now come to my taske; a taske enjoyned me here this day, and that's no leſſe then a <hi>Recantation</hi> of ſome indiſcreet paſſages, in a Sermon which I here preach't at the laſt Aſſizes in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184859:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>this place and Pulpit; the main Charge againſt me in it was, <hi>That I preach't againſt the Exciſe, and Exciſe-Men,</hi> it lyes in the 38 and 39 pages of the Booke, for it was ſince printed; the words then delivered I confeſſe were unadviſedly ſpoken, I was too ſharpe in thoſe expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and while I ſpake of and againſt Biters, I my ſelfe became a Biter. Another paſſage there is which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt, and it is contein'd page 23. where my illguided zeale put me on too farr in pleading for the reſurrection of a <hi>Preſidentiary</hi> Court in theſe Northern-parts; ſo farr, as to charge the <hi>Weſtminſterian Lawyers, That they would engroſſe all the law unto themſelves, as if they meant to make of it, one great Monopoly;</hi> theſe words were unadviſedly ſpoken, and I went too farr in that charge. Another paſſage there is, and that's found page 48. wherein I was very bitter againſt <hi>Rack-renting Land-lords, and Depopulators;</hi> ranking them amongſt the Biters, and the Grinders in the Text: in this I confeſſe I went too farr, it was unadviſedly ſpoken, and gave offence, And indeed I am ſorry that any thing ſhould be ſpoken by me at any time which might juſtly give offence to any, even the leaſt of little ones, much more that ſhould offend Authority; and ſure I am that intentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally I never did, nor ever will do ſo; yet ſeing ſome paſſages in that Sermon have given ſuch occaſion of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, I am heartily ſorry for it, I wiſh they had not fallen from me, much more that they had not been Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
            <p>And theſe paſſages which have been by me here mentioned, I thinke fit to be retracted, and diſowned;
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184859:20"/>particularly that wherein I ſay, <hi>That the government of this Nation is Arbitrary in the male-Adminiſtration of the Exciſe;</hi> which words, together with all other Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretions whatſoever contained in that Sermon and drop't either from my tongue or penne, I do here in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of you all, fully <hi>retract, diſclaime,</hi> and <hi>diſowne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will conclude with one word which his Majeſty ſpake to me himſelfe at the Councell-Table, and it was <hi>cloſe</hi> and <hi>home,</hi> and did more ſilence me, then all that was ſpoke to me beſides, and it was this;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That his Majeſtie thought it was my duty to preach con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience unto the people, and not to meddle with State-affaires:</hi> which words, as they were a ſevere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe for what was paſt, ſo they are a ſerious ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition for the time to come; and I ſhall moſt ſtudiouſly, and exactly henceforth obſerve and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey it, and wiſh all others to do ſo too.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:184859:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
